Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Italian castle archive
1550-1848
1600-1750
GEN MSS 110
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17
(117 boxes - 106 volumes)
The collection contains over 2,000 short manuscripts and printed documents including news bulletins, diplomatic reports, histories, letters, scholarly and practical treatises, legal records, broadsides, genealogies, sermons and orations, plays, and poems. It is especially rich in material concerning the diplomatic role of the Papal States during the War of the Spanish Succession; reports on papal conclaves, instructions to nuncios, and letters from the College of Cardinals; and items pertaining to Ancona, Naples, and the D'Aste family. Other well-documented individuals and events include Innocent X; Olimpia Maidalchini-Pamphili; Queen Christina of Sweden; Cardinal Mazarin; Louis XIV; controversies concerning the Jesuits; the siege of Vienna in 1683 and the 1701 revolt against the Spanish crown in Naples; natural disasters; and the extention of papal authority. In addition, the collection also contains a number of treatises, including works on alchemy, astronomy, cartography, military science, numerology, law, philosophy, and rhetoric, as well as an eight volume edition of the works of the physicist Paretus, and numerous satires on prominent individuals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of H. P. Kraus, with one subsequent purchase.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 106 volumes, dating from c. 1550 to 1770 (with one volume containing items from as late as 1848). Five numbers in the sequence (10, 23, 59, 69, and 77) are missing, and two additional numbers (50a and 98a) have been added. Seven numbers are multi-volume sets. The collection totals 119 volumes in all. Most of the volumes are collections of short manuscripts and printed documents pertaining to a variety of topics. Over 2,000 items are present, about 1,550 in manuscript and roughly 500 in print. All of the documents are on paper and are bound in contemporary vellum. While most of the manuscript documents are written in an italic cursive, a few examples of broad humanist script are present in the collection. A fair number of engravings, woodcuts, ink drawings, and watercolors supplement the text documents.
The entire Italian Castle Archive was donated to Yale by H. P. Kraus, with the exception of volume 98a, which was purchased from Kraus in 1991. The earlier provenance of the Archive is unknown, although the frequent mention of Naples and the D'Aste family leads one to believe that the compilation of the Archive was completed in Southern Italy in the mid to late eighteenth century. Supporting this claim are frequent references to Ancona (where Cardinal Marcello D'Aste was Archbishop in the early 18th century) and Switzerland (where Marcello D'Aste served as Papal Nuncio from 1692-1695). Another member of the family, Donato Antonio D'Aste (d. 1743), was a famous legal scholar who resided in Naples. However, the wide array of documents and the lack of clear early provenance leave the origin of the Archive a mystery. Most of the documents in the collection are from Italy, with a small percentage coming from Spain, France, and the Empire. A vast majority of the items are in Italian and Latin with a few documents in Spanish and French also present. A large number of early printed documents and broadsides may be found in the collection, many of them from the Stamperia Reverendae Camerae Apostolicae. Of the manuscript items, there are some original autograph documents (most notably one of Pope Clement XI, Vol. 29, No. 33a), but most are contemporary copies. Among formal treatises and histories are many letters, news bulletins, and diplomatic reports. There are also a fair number of plays and poems on various topics.
The collection is especially rich in primary source material for the era of the War of Spanish Succession (1700-1713), especially in regards to the role of the Papacy and the Italian peninsula in that conflict. Several volumes contain detailed reports from Papal Conclaves, demonstrating the process by which new Popes were elected from the late Middle Ages to the eighteenth century. There are many sets of instructions to Papal Nuncios, providing an interesting glimpse into the diplomatic relations between the Apostolic See and France, Spain, Portugal, Switzerland, Poland, Flanders, the Austrian Empire, and the various states of Italy.
Series of documents within the collection provide sources and background for a number of influential individuals from the period: Cardinal Mazarin; Queen Christina of Sweden; Olimpia Maidalchini-Pamphili, sister-in-law to Pope Innocent X; King Philip V of Spain; Pope Clement XI; and King Louis XIV of France. Many letters from the Sacred College of the Cardinals provide insight into the politics which surrounded the Papacy in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Certain events are also well-documented within the collection: the readmission of the Jesuits into Venice; the controversy over Jesuit missionaries in China; the 1701 revolt of Naples against the Spanish crown; the 1683 defeat of the Turks at Vienna; various tensions between Pope Alexander VII and the French King Louis XIV; the decline of the De'Medici family of Tuscany; a confrontation between Jesuits and Dominicans at the University of Douai (Flanders) in 1591; and the emergence of the Duchy of Savoy as a player in world politics.
A number of scholarly and practical treatises on a wide variety of topics exist in the collection. These include ones on numerology, alchemy, astronomy, military science, cartography, rhetoric, philosophy, Aristotle, law, history, varnish-making, and equine medicine. There are two student notebooks on the subject of rhetoric, one from the Jesuit College of Rome. Specific histories are given for the cities of Venice, Pisa, Genoa, and Florence, and for the Roman Church. The collection contains an eight volume edition of the works of Paretus, who wrote works on physics soon after Newton, which contain anatomical drawings and a plan for a flying machine. Also present is a 1548 edition of Ptolemy with maps of the Americas added by the editor Giuseppe Moleto.
Other items of note in the collection include:
--Reports and poems about natural disasters such as earthquakes, hailstorms, and a 1660 eruption of Mt. Vesuvio.
--Various treatises and broadsides in support of and against the extention and preservation of Papal authority.
--Poems on subjects which range from the elegaic to the scatalogical.
--Numerous satires--in drama, mock-epic, and verse--of prominent individuals of the period.
--An entrance examination to a Jesuit's German and Hungarian College in Rome.
--Several documents and engravings concerning drama and specific theaters in Rome.
--Watercolor paintings of plans for a fireworks display in Ferrara and of the Battle of Chiari (1701).
--A dictionary of legal terms.
--Records of legal procedings for several cases of murder, heresy, and conspiracy, plus several records of duels, assassinations, and executions.
--Administrative documents of several Nuncios and parish churches.
--Several family histories and genealogical charts.
--Numerous sermons and orations.
--Several reports on Constantinople and accounts of relations with the Ottoman Empire.
--A prayer for lawyers, asking for more arguments and lawsuits.
Knowledge and learning -- History -- Sources; Natural disasters -- Italy -- Sources; Papal courts -- Early works to 1800; Papal nuncios; Pasquinades; Popes -- Election -- Early works to 1800; Satire -- Early works to 1800; Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714 -- Diplomatic history; Theater -- Italy; Theaters -- Italy; Ancona (Italy); Europe -- History -- Sources; Italy -- Civilization -- 1559-1789; Italy -- History -- 1559-1789 -- Sources; Italy -- Intellectual life -- 1559-1789; Naples (Italy) -- History -- 1503-1734; Naples (Kingdom) -- History -- Spanish rule, 1442-1707 -- Sources; Papal States -- Court and courtiers; Papal States -- Diplomatic and consular service -- History -- Sources; Papal States -- Foreign relations -- History -- Sources; Papal States -- History -- Sources; Papal States -- Politics and government; Savoy (France and Italy) -- Foreign relations; Savoy (France and Italy) -- History -- Sources; Venice (Italy) -- History -- 1508-1797; Vienna (Austria) -- History -- Siege, 1683; Alexander, Pope, VII, 1599-1667; Clement, Pope, XI, 1649-1721; Innocent, Pope, X, 1574-1655; Christina, Queen of Sweden, 1626-1689; Louis, King of France, XIV, 1638-1715; Philip, King of Spain, V, 1683-1746; Mazarin, Jules, 1602-1661; Pamphili, Olimpia Maidalchini, 1594-1656; Paretus; D'Aste family; Catholic Church ( Foreign relations); Jesuits ( Controversial literature); Jesuits -- History -- Sources; Jesuits -- Early works to 1800 -- China
- GLI HONESTI PENSIERI
  - Gli Honesti Pensieri. Comedy in five acts. Manuscript. 1 leaf, 115 ff., 1 leaf. (Piece of title page missing, name of author crossed out on title; inscription on end leaf crossed out.) Small 4to. Original limp vellum. (Naples?, c. 1620). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A comedy, probably by a follower of Giovanni Battitsta Della Porta (c. 1538-1615). The inscription on the last leaf is still partly readable: "Per ordine del Sr. Gia. Ant. Basilio da Bari orata per me Sciptione Cardassi in Servicio del..."
- MISCELLANY, 14 manuscripts, comprising 387 pages. 8vo.
  Scope and Contents
  Contemporary limp vellum. Italy (Naples?), c. 1660.
  - Hec Dies quam fecit Dominus exultemus et letemur in ea. Draft for a sermon in Italian. 4 pp. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - St. Matthew 10. Draft of a sermon in Italian, with quotations in Latin. 2-1/2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Himnus hic dat modum vitae, Quo utuntur Jesuitae. Burlesque Latin hymn in Goliardic style, making fun of the Jesuits' love for plentiful food and drink. 3 pp. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oratorio Procuratora. Latin prayer of an attorney. 5 lines, wishing for a perrenial supply of quarrels, lawsuits, etc. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mount Vesuvio, Eruption in July 1660. Hour by hour observation of the eruption of Mt. Vesuvio that took place from July 3-July 10, 1660. 8 pp. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ferrara, Francesco, and Francesco Antonio Scatola. Correspondence concerning poetry, with quotations from Petrarch, Boccaccio, Bemo, etc. In the beginning, Ferrara's sonnet to Scatola. 54 pp. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Canto Primo. 71 octave stanzas of a poem, constituting the first canto. In the manner of G.B. Marino (1569-1625). 36 pp. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Joachimus, Abbot of Fiore. Trattato de operibus sexti temporis. Excerpts from chapter 23, on the Prophet Isaiah. Gioacchino da Fiore (c. 1130-1202) is mentioned in Dante's Divine Comedy. 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Iconography of Popes. Interpretations in Latin and descriptions in Italian of a set of allegoriacal representations of various popes. 24 pp. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alphabetum mysteriosum. Consists of a schematic drawing of the "mysterious alphabet" with explanations and calculations (2 pp.); a list of interpretations of the designations and coats-of-arms of various popes, with biographical data (26 pp.); Archbishop Malachias' prophecies De Pontificibis in the interpretation of Alfonso Ciacconi, a Dominican (2 pp.); and instructions on how to use the Alphabetum in order to determine the length of time a pope stayed in office (1 p.). 31 pp. (some tears). (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Astrampsychi Somniorum Interpretatio. A Latin list of dreams and their significance. "Astrampsychos" was the name given to priests and magi of ancient Egypt and Persia. 5-1/2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nicephorus, Patriarch of Constantinople. Interpretamenta somniorum. Dreams and their significance. Written in Latin Iambic verse and arranged alphabetically. A Greek-Latin version of the Interpramenta Bibliotheca Classica Latina, vol. 129. 8-1/2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ahmad ibn Sirin. Oneirocritica Praefatio, et Somniorum Interpretatio. Excerpts from a Latin translation of a comprehensive work on dream interpretation by the 9th century Arab physician Ahmad ibn Sirin (Ahmed Abu Mazar) which was translated into Latin, Greek, French, and Italian. The Latin edition was published in Frankfurt by Wechel in 1577 with the title Apomasaris Apotelesmata; and a Greek-Latin edition Oneirocritica was published in Paris in 1603, together with Artemidorus' work on dreams. 114 pp. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kabbalah numerica, id est Arti de numeri. An interesting treatise on numeric Kaballah; the art of numbers is treated with chapters on pyramids of summations and partition, on arches of numbers, etc. A Fransiscan monk, Joannes Bernardinus, is quoted on leaf 1 verso and leaf 37 recto. 94 pp. (47 leaves) with tables and diagrams. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- NUMEROLOGICAL MISCELLANY, 7 manuscripts on 273 leaves. 4to. (unless otherwise
  stated). Contemporary vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - Li modi di leggere la zifra. Treatise in Italian on cabalistic numerology. 18 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oraculus Cabalisicus. Table of letters and numbers from which to calculate the election of Pope Innocent X (1644-1655). Table of 1 page. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - De ludo numerorum. 65 leaves, 1 p. Treatise in Latin on numerology; contains among others chapters and tables on Alphabetum essentiale-Alphabetum accidentale; Extensio Numerorum ascendentes-... descendentes; Proportiones quam Improportiones; Modus de habendis numeris..., etc. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - De cuspidibus de Horoscopo. Treatise in Latin on the significance of the Zodiac signs. Table and 9 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ludus Numerorum. Treatise in Latin on numerology, with cabalistic and astrological implications. Chapters I-IV. 10 leaves. 8vo. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - (Numerological Tables). Folio folded to 4to. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Papiniano da Villanova. Libro della Geomantia. An Italian treatise on divination. The author could not be identified by Thorndike (vol. IV, p. 473), who places him in the 16th century and locates one manuscript of this treatise in the Vatican Library (Vatic. Reg. Suev. 1319). It was apparently never printed. 156 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- COLLECTION OF POEMS, 59 manuscripts on 226 leaves. Folio. Contemporary
  vellum. Italy, 17th and 18th centuries.
  - Instruzione Per La Vita Civile di un Giovane Nobile. 17 leaves. Didactic Italian poem in blank verse, giving instructions for the conduct of life to a young nobleman. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nappini, Bartolomeo (called Polipodio Calabro). 24 poems, 20 leaves, (foliated 18-37). Poems by the Calabrian poet Bartolomeo Nappini (d. 1717), who wrote under the pseudonym Polipodio Calabro, consisting of 20 sonnets, 2 elegies, 1 poem (in praise of the pig) in tercets, and one satirical poem. The poems are done in the "stile pedantesco," also known as the "stile fidenziano," which forces the pedantic Latin jargon of schoolmasters upon the Italian language. The last edition of Nappini's poems came out at Guastalla in 1780 and it is a bibliographical rarity. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Il Dottor Boccaleone Consola Valerio Notaro esser gli morta la Moglie & Figli. 7 leaves, numbered ff. 38-44. Italian canzone of 37 octave stanzas, possibly also by Bartolomeo Nappini. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - (Consiglio dell'Oracolo in Prendere Moglier). 1 page (f. 45). A humorous oracle as guidance in selecting a wife. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Regali Lasciati ad un Amico nella Partenza. 10 leaves, numbered ff. 46-55. Parting from Rome, the (anonymous) author describes in humorous verses the presents he leaves behind for a friend, a theme reminiscent of Francois Villon's Grand Testament. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - L'Ignoranza Escaldada.--Racconto (se che fece un grazioso Pittore). 2 leaves, numbered ff. 56-57. Two canzone, extolling ignorance; a rough paraphrase from the prophet Habakkuk. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fortuna e Fato. 2 leaves, numbered ff. 58-59. Two sonnets and several poems on the subject of fortune and fate; includes excerpts from Matteo Bojardo, G.B. Guarini, and an epigram by Ausonius. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fugacita dell Vita Umana. 3 pages, numbered ff. 60-61. Poem in rhymed quartets on the fleetingness of human life. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - De Sogni. 2 pages, numbered ff. 62. A poem on dreams, in blank verse ("Verso sciolto"). (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chocolata.--Della Chocolata.--Colmenero de Ledesma, Antonio. 13 leaves, numbered ff. 64-67. Two early poems on chocolate, one in Latin, the other in Italian. At the end is an excerpt from the first Italian edition of Colmenero's treatise on chocolate (1667; Palau 56907). Colmenero da Ledesma, a Spanish physician, was the first to write a monograph (1631) on chocolate, the drink made from cocoa beans that had come to Europe from Mexico. Only in the early part of the 18th century did chocolate become a fashionable beverage in Europe. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Le Vignate. 11 leaves, numbered ff. 77-87. Italian poem in Anacreontic verse on the delight of autumn in the countryside. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Volpe, Conte della. All'Eminentissimo Principe Il Signor Cardinal Conti per la Nascita del secondo Nipote. 1 page, numbered ff. 88. The poem to Cardinal Conti is signed Cleogene Naffio, the name given to Volpe as a member of the Academy Arcadia. It is dated Rome, 1729. This Conte della Volpe seems not to be one of the famous brothers Volpe who were active in Padua at this time and established the Tipographia Volpi-Cominiano. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Copia del Memoriale dato a Il Sig. Papa Clemente XII. Corsini. 3 leaves, numbered ff. 89-91. Copy of a memorandum, in the form of a poem in tercets, to Pope Clement XII (1730-1740). (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - In Lode del Porco. (In Lode del Prosciutto). 9 pages, numbered ff. 92-96. A poem in Anacreontic style in praise of a pig (8 pages), followed by a sonnet on a delicious ham. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - L'Imperator Carlo V fa pigliare un Faccino. 3 leaves, numbered ff. 97-98. A satirical canzone on the Emperor Charles V who was put to shame by the sense of justice of a drunken porter whom he had brought to the royal palace. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sonetto Peripatetica. -Enigma Paripatetica. 2 pages, numbered ff. 100. Two "peripatetic" sonnets in the grotesque style of Burchellio (1400-1449). (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - A Monsignor...de Brevi, che promise cert'assagio di vini precosi. 6 leaves, numbered ff. 101-105. A canzone in praise of wine, with the refrain "Monsignor quel vino aspetto," dedicated to a Monsignor de Brevi who had promised the author to let him taste precious wines. On the last page is a drinking song of wandering students (goliards). (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bella Dona richiede ad un Cacciatore, un Augellino, ed egli cosi risponde. -La Corte. -Grazioissima risoluzione, 1690. -Ad un Marchese che portova la Carozza con certi Cavalli. -Epitaffio alla Sepoltura del Colangeli. 5 pages, numbered ff. 106-108. 5 sonnets in a burlesque style, reminiscent of Berni, on various events and persons in Rome. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Gloria, et Honore...della Santita di Nostro Sig. Papa Clemente XI, Anno 1714. 1 page (f. 108 verso). Sonnet in praise of Pope Clement XI (1700-1721). (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Al Serenissimo Eugenio di Savoia per La Disfatta de Turchi in Ungheria li 5 Agosto 1716. 2 pages, (f. 109). Two sonnets in praise of Prince Eugene of Savoy and his victory over the Turks. By Don Angelo Ricci (?). (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Capitolo della Zappa. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 110-113. A burlesque poem in tercets on the hoe; in imitation of the style of Berni. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - All'Indiscretezza del Padre Ciceri. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 110-113. A burlesque poem in tercets ("capitolo"), ridiculing a friar, dated 1712. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Ringraziamento per 4 Fiaschi di Vino. -per dieci Fiaschi di Vino. -(Una Giavane si Lamenta...un marito troppo veccio). -All Abbati Montani...Un Cane rubba certa carne di mano. -Impostura all'autore. 3 leaves, numbered ff. 118-120. Six humorous sonnets; thanking for bottles of wine; an 18 year old girl married to a 67 year old husband (referring to a "true story" of 1744), etc. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - La Birba. -Dorme Spensierato. -Amante che scuopre L'Amore alla sua Donna. -Notturna Serenata. 7 leaves, numbered ff. 121-127. Three popular songs and one sonnet. The song La Birba (The Scoundrel) has a choral refrain "Eviva La Birba e Chi L'invento"; the two other songs are sung after the same melody as La Birba. The texts only are given. The sonnet is reminiscent and seems to anticipate the style of Guiseppe Belli (1791-1863), the greatest poet in Roman dialect. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Alli Virtuosi Tabbacanti. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 128-129. One sonnet, "scherzo Poetico," and epigrams in Latin, Spanish, and Italian on tobacco and taking snuff. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Consiglio ad un Amico. 1 page (fol. 129 verso). A sonnet, based on a quotation from Cicero, advising to consult the wisdom of the past. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Sogno, accaduto nel Mese di Luglio 1746. 28 leaves, numbered ff. 130-157. A long poem of a dream. At the end a note stating that this poem is "un Compendio Teorico della Guerre di 10 Anni." (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - El Genio Romanesco. -In Laude Nicolai Salvii. 2 pages, numbered ff. 158. Italian sonnet and a Latin poem in praise of the architect Nicola Salvi, creator of the Fontana di Trevi. Both poems are dated 1744. Salvi's fountain, begun in 1732, was finished only in 1762. The style of the sonnet is similar to that of the great poet in Roman dialect, G.G. Belli. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Sopra ad un Podagroso. -Rimedio per guerir La Podagra. 5 pages, numbered ff. 159-161. Two humorous poems on gout; a canzone, with the refrain "Simonelli ha la Podagra," and a sonnet on the cure of the gout. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Procura trouvare un'Innamorata. 1 page (f. 161 verso). A sonnet on the difficulty of finding a sweetheart to one's taste. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - De Ducenda Uxore. 2 pages (f. 162). Two satirical poems on marriage; Latin distychs in the style of Ovid and the Italian sonnet. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Ottave giocose Sopra Le Moroide. -Rimedio per Le Moroide, La Vendetta. 8-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 163-167. Humorous poems on hemorrhoids and their cure, the latter referring to Simone Maiolo's Dies Caniculares. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - La Forza del Destino. 1 page (f. 167 verso). A sonnet. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - La Vendemnia. 5 pages, numbered ff. 168-170. A long poem (text for a song) on vintage time, with the choral refrain "Alla Mozza Donne belle." (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Consiglio agli Ammogliati. 1 page (f. 170 verso). A sonnet of advice to married people. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - La Caccia. -Quest'è L'estrema volta Ingrata Pastorella. -La Vite overo Autunno. 2 leaves, numbered ff. 171-172. Three pastoral songs: on the hunt; a lover's lament; on the delights of autumn. (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Ottave sopra alcune spose. 2 pages (f. 173). Four stanzas, each with a moral ("senso") on married women. (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Poeta assistente per la Festa di S. Luigi Gonzaga alla musica nella Chiesa di S. Ignazio...ricordandosi si S. Romualdo Monaco Benedettino... 1 page, numbered fol. 173 (bis). An anti-Jesuit sonnet. (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Grimaldi, Stefano. Del gran Marte de i Re... 1 page (f. 173 bis, verso). Sonnet by the Genoese ambassador to the court of Louis XIV to a lady of the French court. On account of this sonnet, Grimaldi was banned from the court for a time. (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Affetto et industria de Sorci. -Morale di Felicita. 1 leaf (f. 174). Two sonnets: one on mice, with all lines ending on the same rhyme; one on happiness. (Box 4, Folder 40)